<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"><title>Peter Wooldridge's Blog - Diabetes</title><link href="https://peterwooldridge.me/" rel="alternate"></link><link href="https://peterwooldridge.me/feeds/diabetes.atom.xml" rel="self"></link><id>https://peterwooldridge.me/</id><updated>2021-02-03T17:40:00+00:00</updated><subtitle>I'm a Data Scientist with Type 1 Diabetes. Most of the time I'll write about one or the other.</subtitle><entry><title>A serious rethink on carbs taught to me by Mastering Diabetes</title><link href="https://peterwooldridge.me/a-serious-rethink-on-carbs-taught-to-me-by-mastering-diabetes.html" rel="alternate"></link><published>2021-02-03T17:40:00+00:00</published><updated>2021-02-03T17:40:00+00:00</updated><author><name>Peter Wooldridge</name></author><id>tag:peterwooldridge.me,2021-02-03:/a-serious-rethink-on-carbs-taught-to-me-by-mastering-diabetes.html</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;I've observed the pattern so many thousands of times:
eating high carb foods cause the biggest fluctuations in my post-meal glucose.
Therefore, high carbs are problematic and best avoided. This is the deeply ingrained mental model
I've been working with for the last 25 years to manage my type 1 …&lt;/p&gt;</summary><content type="html">&lt;p&gt;I've observed the pattern so many thousands of times:
eating high carb foods cause the biggest fluctuations in my post-meal glucose.
Therefore, high carbs are problematic and best avoided. This is the deeply ingrained mental model
I've been working with for the last 25 years to manage my type 1 diabetes. How could this be wrong?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Well, owing to some extra free time over lockdown, I came across the Mastering Diabetes book.
I've had so many aha moments reading this book and relating the evidenced based approaches with my own experience
with T1D. One of the many things I took away was a complete rethink on carbs.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class="figure align-center" style="width: 60%"&gt;
&lt;img alt="" src="https://peterwooldridge.me/md_book.jpeg" /&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div class="line-block"&gt;
&lt;div class="line"&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The book states that labelling carbs as the enemy has actually given rise to a whole
host of the confusion that we see today around carbs and diabetes.
The carbs story is much more nuanced for two main reasons.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Firstly, in order to talk meaningfully about carbs it's important
to distinguish between refined and unrefined. Refined carbs are essentially those that have undergone
processing of one kind or another for example removing the bran from a grain and
grinding the grain to make flour. These types of carbs tend to get absorbed very quickly by the body. The opposite
is true of unrefined carbs which are composed of longer chain carbohydrate molecules that release glucose into the bloodstream
much more slowly. Plant foods are a great source of unrefined carbs.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The second reason is that high glucose values following a high carb meal are
actually indicative of a state of insulin resistance and not an issue with
carbs themselves. Insulin resistance is a state whereby the body's tissues have
a lower level of response to insulin
meaning glucose cannot be absorbed as efficiently by cells leaving it lingering in the blood.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;My understanding up to this point has been that insulin resistance was more of a type 2 diabetes problem
but the book clarified that it can and does occur in all types of diabetes.
The mechanisms that bring about insulin resistance are in fact the same regardless
of types of diabetes. Insulin resistance is caused by:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p class="center"&gt;&lt;em&gt;The accumulation of fat in tissues that are not designed to store large quantities of fat&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;For type 1's like myself, becoming more sensitive to insulin has the advantage that I need to
take less of the stuff. Less insulin means a smaller margin for error and therefore a greater
chance of keeping my glucose levels steady.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Whilst managing carbs more easily and taking less insulin are good enough reasons for me to work
on become as sensitive as possible to insulin, the other more pertinent reason to be doing it is
because insulin resistance is the cause of whole
host of diabetes complications, basically you name it, it's there.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Tight glucose control alone is not sufficient alone to minimise risk
of future complications. This is backed up by some interesting research such as &lt;a class="reference external" href="https://care.diabetesjournals.org/content/26/5/1374"&gt;this&lt;/a&gt;
paper which concluded in a study of 603 type 1 patients insulin resistance
was a better predictor of future coronary artery disease than anything else including glucose control!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I really love the evidenced based approach Cyrus and Robby have taken with their book and wider programme. I've just
enrolled in their online coaching course so expect more posts on this topic soon. In the meantime, I'd
encourage anyone with diabetes to read this book, it taught me so many things that I know are going to be valuable for the long term.&lt;/p&gt;
</content></entry></feed>