<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"><title>Peter Wooldridge's Blog - Tech</title><link href="https://peterwooldridge.me/" rel="alternate"></link><link href="https://peterwooldridge.me/feeds/tech.atom.xml" rel="self"></link><id>https://peterwooldridge.me/</id><updated>2021-01-31T12:15:00+00:00</updated><subtitle>I'm a Data Scientist with Type 1 Diabetes. Most of the time I'll write about one or the other.</subtitle><entry><title>The single UNIX setting that always saves me time</title><link href="https://peterwooldridge.me/unix_efficiency.html" rel="alternate"></link><published>2021-01-31T12:15:00+00:00</published><updated>2021-01-31T12:15:00+00:00</updated><author><name>Peter Wooldridge</name></author><id>tag:peterwooldridge.me,2021-01-31:/unix_efficiency.html</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;Anyone who spends a lot of time on the command line will know the frustration of trying to locate a previous command from your bash history. The following configuration allows a simple one button ability to search through your bash history using the up and down arrows. Unlike other approaches …&lt;/p&gt;</summary><content type="html">&lt;p&gt;Anyone who spends a lot of time on the command line will know the frustration of trying to locate a previous command from your bash history. The following configuration allows a simple one button ability to search through your bash history using the up and down arrows. Unlike other approaches like CTRL-R, which search the history for a substring anywhere in the command, this method will search the history using the text to the left of the cursor. So, if I type &lt;code&gt;ls&lt;/code&gt; and then up I will cycle through the most recent commands starting with &lt;code&gt;ls&lt;/code&gt;. I personally find this makes it a much faster way to locate previous commands. To set it, simply add the following lines to ~/.inputrc:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class="highlight"&gt;&lt;pre&gt;&lt;span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="s2"&gt;&amp;quot;\e[A&amp;quot;&lt;/span&gt;: history-search-backward
&lt;span class="s2"&gt;&amp;quot;\e[B&amp;quot;&lt;/span&gt;: history-search-forward
&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
</content></entry></feed>